hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today in the spring
board series we are going to cover The
async annotation there are lot more
things to cover in aing annotation and
lot more things happen behind it we will
see in depth but before I proceed
further this three Java topics I would
say that it's a prerequisite if you want
to understand the using annotation
properly you should know how to create a
thread and its life cycle what is
threadpool and threadpool executor and
what is Future callable and completable
Future and how it works okay
so let's start this so here in this
first let me in very brief I will tell
you about threadpool and threadpool
executor and I want to make sure that we
are all in same page right we have the
same understanding of the threadpool and
threadpool executor but please check out
this three videos which are in depth and
it is available in Javas series which is
a prerequisite to understand our sync
annotation okay what is thread pool
thread pool is a collection of threads
which are available to perform the
submitted
task once the task completed threads get
back to the thread pool and wait for the
new task to
assign means threat can be
reused okay so let's understand with
this diagram so in so there is something
understand is there is something called
of pool in which we have pre-created the
threats we have pre-created the threads
and available to pick the task now there
is some Q available and application also
involved which is submitting the task so
this task gets
submitted into this queue
first now any thread which is free in
this pool
will pick the task from the front of the
queue and start processing it at once
the task is completed the thread goes
back to this pool and now is available
to pick any other task from the
queue okay so this threadpool executor
involves couple of things like to
understand this there is something
called right
minimum pool size minimum pool size
means what should be the minimum number
of threads which should be
pre-created maximum pool
size what is the maximum number of
threads we can
create that is the number which says
maximum pool size Q
size what should be the length of this Q
how many tasks it can accommodate so
this size tells this so determining this
thing is very a good interview question
also and determining these three things
involve lot of consideration like what
is your CPU memory and all these things
which I have explained this in this
video thread pool executor in the Java
series okay so but for understanding
this threadpool executor let's say that
minimum pool size is two maximum pool
size is four and the Q size is three
just for now and let's understand the
behavior so that we all are in the same
page that how the thread pool executor
works so now let's say that you have a Q
which size 3
012 and you have a pool of two threads
thread one thread two which is currently
available minimum pool size so it is
free now let's say task is
coming task one comes so task one goes
into the Q and thread one will pick it
so task one is now getting processed by
thread one so this is now
busy now task two is coming task two
will be put into the
Q
right and task two will be picked by
thread two so thread 2 will take it and
start processing
it now both the threads are busy now
let's say they haven't completed it so
the pool is currently there is no free
threads available okay okay now let's
say that task Three is coming so task
three will go into the Q So currently
both this task one and two has already
been removed because they have been
processing so task Three is coming so
now here if you see task three is there
any thread available which can pick this
task currently no both the threads
thread one and thread two are busy so
task three Will Wait into the que now
let's say task four is coming
so task four will go into the back of
the queue is there any thread available
which can pick no both are busy so it
will wait into the queue now task five
is coming again it will goes into the
back of the queue and it will wait till
any thread is
free now task six is coming now what
would happen to the task say is there
any thread available no thread both the
threads are busy so minimum pool size
both the threads are busy is there any
available size available space in the Q
no Q is full there is no space so what
shall we do for the task six shall we
discard it no then it goes and check the
max pool size hey what is the max pool
size can I create more thread yes Max
pool size says that the maximum number
of thread in a pool can be four So
currently we have only two so it will
create a new thread uh thread three and
now thread three will pick it Tas six
will get picked by thread three
so Tas six is going to pick by thread
three and it is not there into the
Q now let's say that task 7 is coming
task 7 it will say hey any thread
available thread so thread 3 is already
processing task six here any available
thread
there in the pool
no any space available in the queue no
so shall we discard the task 7 it will
check what should be the maximum pool
size four what is available currently
three we can create one more so it will
create new thread thread four and that
will
processing task
7 thread
four okay so this is also getting
processed now let's say task eight is
coming what would happen to the task
eight is there any new thread or free
thread available no is there any space
available in the queue no it will check
what is the maximum pool size I can
create four so what is the number of
thread 1 2 3 4 already you have reached
to the max now you can't do anything
this will get
rejected now let's say that the thread
one has processed the task one completed
and it is now available now thread one
is now available into the Q back again
so thread one is now available now it
goes back to the pool again so what
thread one will do it will check the Q
and it will take the front of the Q so
task three so task three will get now
process by thread one so now it is now
getting
processed
so this is a very basic understanding of
thread pool and thread pool executor
which I have explained in depth
here and this is a semantics like this
is how we create a threadpool in Java we
create new thread pool executor object
provide a minimum pool size maximum pool
size and what should be the Q
size there is something called keep
alive time time unit ARS which you will
get to know in this video itself right
but for their Simplicity and the basic
understanding and just kind of a quick
recap these three things are important
minimum pool size maximum pool size and
Q size which I have already told you how
these three plays a crucial role in this
task
sequencing
okay now let's start understanding how a
sync annotation
works so a sync annotation is used to
Mark method that should run a SN
synchronously right asynchronously means
in a new thread so when you start a
particular application let's say so it's
always starting in a one let's say
thread one or sometime we call it as a
main
thread right so always one thread will
get picked and start your program now
what happen is whenever you have put a
certain method as
using right we are telling that hey
create a new thread it will create some
new thread let's say thread two
and that method will get executed in by
this new thread but our main thread is
get now unblocked and we'll continue
processing further okay so here let's
say we have a sync
method so a sync method it will initiate
a new thread and that will now continue
processing whatever we have task
available in that method so it is
getting executed by the new thread which
is got spawned but the main thread which
is running that get unblocked and that
will continue processing
ahead
okay so runs in a new thread without
blocking the main thread so take this
example so here first thing first we
have to put this annotation in our main
application spring boot application
where we have put this annotation right
at theate springbot application so we
have to put an annotation right at
theate enable a sing what is the purpose
of this annotation the purpose of this
annotation is once you once a spring
boot sees that hey this annotation is
present it will create a bean for a SN
classes which is required for processing
the using task there are so many things
using interceptors and there are so many
other classes which get involved but
they will only get their objects or
their beings will get only be created
when you will put this annotation
otherwise spring unnecessarily will not
create an or create a bean for those
classes okay so whenever we have to use
an a sync functionality
for The async annotation we have to tell
the spring that hey create a bean for
those async classes also so unable a
sync is The
annotation now I have written one very
very simple method rest controller very
simple API you already know at the get
mapping get user and very simple method
so here I'm printing inside get user
method whenever uh we will invoke this
API
/ API SLG get
user it this will get invoked and it
will print inside get user method and
I'm printing what is the thread name so
generally this is the main thread name
right the main thread now here if you
see that I am invoking an another method
which is inside user service
class and it is calling the using method
so this is the user service class right
user service class managed by Spring
ussing method so this is the method
which is getting invoked and now this
method I have put at the rate
using now once I have put at theate
using mean I am telling a spring that
hey this method should get be processed
by new thread instead of the main thread
which is running so this thread is the
main thread which is uh which is running
now when this method get invoked
This Thread should be the new thread so
this I just printing the thread name
inside using method name and what is the
thread name so this should be different
than the main
thread so if we run this and see the
output inside get user method this one
inside get user method so this is like
your main thread and here inside using
method task one so here the thread name
is Task one housing method what is the
thread name task one so here if you you
see that these are the two different
threads now if you run continuously so
here I am running continuously so I have
hit the Endo get user then again I hit
the
Endo get user just to show you that
every time you will hit it will create a
new
thread
here earlier it was created thread one
then thread two then thread three then
thread four so every time a new thread
will get
created inside using method task uh Task
5 so this is the thread name it has
given new using method 6 7 8 right new
assing method generally I am printing
the thread name so here if you see every
time you will
hit it will just create
a new
thread
okay so this is what a sync annotation
does
looks very simple right but not
so now let's come to this question how
does this async annotation create a new
thread here when I put an a sync
annotation and whenever a main thread is
invoking this it creates a new thread
like okay thread created inside using
thread which which thread This Thread so
it is different then what's your parent
thread so how does this using annotation
creates a new thread many places you
will find that spring boot uses by
default simple using task executor which
create new thread every time
blindly right so here if you say I have
just put at the rate using nothing else
I haven't provided any thread executor
like or thread pool executor that this
should be the minimum number of pool
maximum number of pool or even pool is
present or not I haven't told
that so many places you will see they
will say that hey Spring boot by default
using simple assing task executor means
blindly create a new thread every time
it is required I will say this is not a
fully correct answer
and you might get stuck in a followup
questions but let's understand like what
is the right answer and how this exactly
work
internally okay but before I proceed
further here if you see if you see below
the spring boot framework code so this
is one spring boot internally won some
async class here if you see async
execution Interceptor inside this you
will find this code what it say first it
will try to identify get default
executor if it able to find some default
executor when we when I say default
executor considered as a thread pool
executor where you have a minimum pool
size maximum pool size what should be
the Q size like this so first spring
also try to see hey can I use any
default
executor if default executor is
null then only it use spring assing task
uh simple assing task executor this
one but
what but in what all scenario it able to
find a default executor here if you see
this if you see this example above where
I have just put at the rate enable aing
and at the rate a sing so it is using
task one task 2 task
three and task five task six task 7 task
eight and if you go proceed further it
will again start from task one task two
task three means there you will see that
the question should have come to you if
you do debug right hey I am using at
theate using and from everywhere else
according to their logic a spring boot
should have used simple assing task
executor so it should have create new
thread every time so it should be like 8
9 10 11 12 but after 8 why again it's
going back to the one is there any some
kind of uh thread pool
involved so answer lies here and we will
see that first spring boot see any
default executor it can use if it if the
answer is yes it will use that if the
answer is no then it will use Simple
assing task
executor now Let's see different use
cases and we will find our
answer use case
one I am creating a simple spring boot
application I have just put ad theate
enable using letting spring boot knows
that hey create a bean for usync classes
because I'm going to use at theate async
operation if you see my app config atate
configuration it's empty I haven't
provide any kind of functionality or my
custom thread pool execu or
nothing now in the class I have put one
assing method similarly like above I
have told I have put at the rate
aing right and I have one controller
which calls this method I have showed
you above right let's say that that
controller is still present there which
invoking this using
method okay so now what would is what
would happen here now this is exactly
the same as the above B one how after
thread task 8 again task one task two
the thread name coming so what would
happen so during application startup
when you start an
application spring boot sees that no
threadpool task
executor present so it creates its
default threadpool task
executor so what springb does is it
check hey
does developer or does application
Define any threadpool executor or
threadpool task executor no we have not
provided anything so what spring boot
does is spring boot creates its own or
creates its default thread pool task
executor with below
configuration core pool size means
minimum pool size
eight maximum pool size is your in do
max
value and the Q capacity is again
integer do max
value okay but this is how it created
and that's where we see that when I run
it it say 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
so8 8 threads were available so they
picked it right after that when I put
again
it again started from 1 2 3 4 5 6 right
no new thread created but here if you
see it has certain disadvantage also
because the max pool size are very big
even the Q size are very
big
okay so it has certain disadvantage and
also I will tell uh before coming to the
disadvantage of this I will tell you
that here spring boot tried to see
threadpool task executor so so see there
is something called thread pool
executor which is Java plain Java and
there is something called thread pool
task
executor this is a spring this is a
spring
wrapper this is a spring wrapper around
this okay so spring boot sees what
threadpool task executor this one
okay so here if you see the threadpool
task executor is nothing but a spring
boot object which is just a wrapper
around threadpool executor so here if
this is the class threadpool task
executor if you go inside this
internally what it is doing creating a
plain Java threadpool executor only so
it's just a wrapper which again creates
a same threadpool executor plain Java
threadpool executor
okay so when you provide this kind of
code is spring boot again check this
threadpool task executor if no
threadpool task executor
present it will create its own default
one with this
configuration and this configuration has
certain disadvantage which is not
recommended all to use first under
utilization of thre
underutilization of thread means with
fixed mean pool size and unbounded Q I
told you the flow what happen the
maximum pool size will only come into
the picture when the pools this are busy
and the Q is totally filled but here in
this if you see the Q size is too big
it's a very rare that this quebe will
get filled up so means
even though your application can afford
that okay I can create new threads but
still new thread will not get created
because the que is not yet filled so
that's why I say that the first problem
with this under utilization of thread
even though you can afford to create a
new thread more than eight but it won't
create because the Q is not filled
itself because Q size is too
big high latency since the Q size is too
big they will keep keep on waiting so
now let's say that your all the eight
threads are busy thread 1 to thread
eight are busy now any task which are
coming task N9 task 10 they will keep on
waiting into the Q until Q is not filled
up before it a new thread get spawned
from the max pool size so here if you
see since the Q capacity is too huge
this task will keep on appending and
they will keep on waiting for for this
out of this eight thread only to get
free and then they will pick
it right we we are not creating new
threats from the max pool size because Q
is not getting filled up so they will
keep on waiting into the Q
itself so high latency is another
problem with this one threat
exhaustion threat exhaustion is there
that see it is very rear rare in this
thread exhaustion but it's possible how
come see there is no control coree pool
size 8 Q capacity is this and maximum
pool size is this everything is like not
infinite right what if like core pool
size 8 all thread one to thread 8 are
busy the Q become filled completely
filled 0 2 2 1 4 7 4 8 3 6 4 6 all the
task got filled up let's say and now it
will start creating threads from the max
till the max pool size is not reached
and now let's say that because of some
issue it is keep on creating a new
threads and this limit is also reached
now you are out of threat and your
application will crash it's very
unlikely here because the size are too
big but thread exhaustion is possible
because nobody is controlling that we
should get stop and they keep on
creating the threats till it is
finished another is high memory usage
see each thread needs some
memory now just assume that if you are
creating so many thread now let's say
that all eight threads are
created Q is full now you try to create
a thread still this Max pool sizes reach
you are creating so many threads and
there is a chance that high memory
usage your system will perform uh
performance will get
degrade so there are so many see these
are just four disadvantage if you go
further right there are so many other
disadvantage comes into the
picture but these four are very
sufficient to say that we should not go
with the default threadpool executor
functionality so we should never use
this so use case one we should never use
this we just put atate unable assn and
just put at theate assn
no so what should we do let's see the
use case
2 creating our own custom threadpool
task executor right I am saying task
executor means spring one not the plain
Java this is a rapper which internally
will create a plain Java one so here if
you see in the spring boot application I
am creating atate enable assing it will
tell a spring boot to uh initialize
class class ES which is
required and this is the method the same
method where I'm putting at the a sync
only first first ignore this I'll tell
you first Focus only on this one it's
exactly the same right at theate assing
I'm putting and this assing method it's
just printing
this now inside this configuration I am
providing my own threadpool task
executor own threadpool task task
executor so I am creating a new object
of threadpool task
executor providing a minimum pool size
two maximum pool size four and the Q
size is three so here you know that in
the plain Java I have already told you
in plain Java how you can do it in plain
Java you can do it like this right new
threadpool executor minimum maximum like
this right but here in the spring it's
just a wrapper right so it's a little
bit uh
uh read like readability is better so
I'm putting core pool size here you can
set the max pool size you can set the Q
capacity and even you can give the uh
thread name prefix like I want this
thread name prefix my thread
hyphen and you can initialize
it now what would happen when I start an
application
during application
startup what spring boot say that spring
boot will try to
identify if you see this
code First Step spring board will try to
identify see any default executor it can
use and
yes now here in this case during
application startup spring boot sees
that threadpool task executor Bean is
already present we because we have
created a bean right for this so this
Bean is already
present so spring boot will not create
its own threadpool executor it will use
over itself so see even though we
haven't tell here which one to use but
is still it will use this
only
right so during application startup
spring boot sees that the threadpool
task executor be is present so this will
make it default so either you use it you
will get the same or either if you
provide the name which explicitly
executor so here the bean I have
provided a
name so the same name you can give it
here so either you specifically mention
that okay I want to usey use my
executor then also it will use this only
even if you don't use this and if you
even if you just put at the syn it will
not use Simple assing task executor that
is wrong it will use over only why I
already told you it first try to see is
there any default is there any
threadpool task executor being present
if no spring board creates its
own if it is present the spring board
use that only so now here if you see
that in both the scenario whether you
use it without name or with name the
output would be same now if you call
multiple time so I'm calling multiple
times so each time you will see
that that this is the main thread and
when our using method invoke my thread
one so here if you see I given the
prefix my thread
hyphen second time my thread two so I
have what is the minimum pool size I
have given two right and threads are got
free as soon as there is nothing High
processing I'm doing so the third time
I'm running again this only pck
next time I'm running thread two pick
next time I'm running again thread one
pick so here if you see this two threads
are able to handle all the
task and if we have to understand the
que and all so let's say that I am
putting sleep in the using method so in
the using method I purposely added the
sleep after putting inside using method
and I have put a sleep just to make sure
that okay once the threat pick this they
busy and they are not get free and then
test it so now what happen is say first
time I
ran minimum pool size is two Max is 4
and the Q size is three right 2 43 yeah
so now here if you see task one
come thread one got picked so only one
left second task comes thread two got
picked so no free threads available in
the minimum pool it's now zero now more
task is coming so it is just putting
into the que so here if you see no
thread grid created so it just putting
task three task four task
five now here if you see task six is
coming what happened is another thread
got invoke because maximum is four so
one more thread comes in a new thread
comes into the
picture now that is also free uh that is
also busy now another thread is
coming uh another task is coming seven
all three this two and this three are
busy Q is full again I can create one
more so threat four
created
and task 7 is getting processed so this
is also busy now eight is coming task
eight all four threads are busy Q is
full task is get
rejected okay task get got rejected so
now here if you see that the thread pool
is working like how we want it based
upon our analysis what should be good
for our system we have come up with this
number and now it's working as expected
we are not allowing that you can create
more threats apart from this
number so this is you can say
recommended
solution okay and one one answer you
have got that even though we are using
at the rate
using it is not picking simple assing
task executor because first it will
check any threadpool task executor be is
present and yes it is
present now let's understand the use
case 3 very very interesting use
case creating our own threadpool
executor but the Java one in the
previous one we have created a custom
thread pool task executor a spring one
which spring looks for but what if we
create a Java 1 here now here if you see
the same thing I have put at theate
enable assing and now here I am using at
theate async
only but here I am using plain Java uh
plane
Java to create a threadpool executor not
threadpool task executor which is for
spring I'm using plain Java but I am
creating a bean for the
executor now what would
happen What would happen at if I run
this will it will this executor be
picked no what would happen is I told
you during application startup spring
boot sees that hey
threadpool executor the Java 1 Bean is
present so it do not create its own
default or try to even look for
threadpool task executor
itself so spring rapper one is like a
second priority the first priority is
that hey if the Java threadpool executor
we have itself
defined if you if you use threadpool
task executor internally it will create
a jav threadpool executor this command
but if we itself have provided the
threadpool executor right this executor
is now instance of threadpool
executor okay so since we have provided
this spring board will not even look for
this threadpool task executor so now in
this case what would happen
is this one the default executor come as
null and once it is come as null it will
pick simple assing task
executor
right so that's the you can say that the
use case where it only pick
simple a sync thread executor where we
have provided our own plain Java
threadpool
executor right then spring boot will not
even create an instance of threadpool
task executor
right and if you are using a
syn then at this point of time a spring
will go for simple using task executor
now here if you see if I run now here if
you see the first time application main
run it pick simple assing task executor
one second time 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 see
after8 it just keep on 10 11 now it will
not not go after it again
one it will just keep on going if you
keep on hitting it will keep on going
now here is the name thread name itself
say using simple using task executor
because we have provided This Thread
pool executor the plain Java
1 so what to do we we have to provide
this we have to here provide a proper
name okay
whenever you have used the plain Java
threadpool
executor we have to tell specifically
spring boot that hey use this
executor assing and give that executor
name then it will pick your thread one
thread 2 my thread one my thread 2 so
whatever I am
giving okay so always remember whenever
you are using plain Java executor
your uh so you have to specifically
provide the name to
theing but if you are using spring
threadpool thread threadpool task
executor without even providing it will
work without even providing it will work
like this because the code will look
for any threat task executor
present okay and also you know that this
simple using task executor is not
recommended because of the same reason
thread exhaustion since blindly creating
a new thread with every using request
might lead up to thread
exhaustion thread creation overhead
since threads are not reused thread
management like creation destroying is
an additional
overhead High memory usage every thread
requires some memory let's say uh if
there are more threats currently running
in parallel they require more memory so
your application performance
degrades so we should not use like if
you are
using your plain Java threadpool
executor then you should not use add
theate as sync simply you have to use a
specifically the name so that this get
picked
up okay I hope
this
uh I know that the answer of this
solution what is the default
executor is picked up by Spring is not
that straightforward so with this three
use cases I told you what is the default
behavior and what should be the
recommended solutions to
use but let's say
that if you see that by this point of
time you say that hey I don't want all
this confusion man use case one use case
2 use case
three in the use case one I can use
directly at the rate US sing in use case
2 I can also use at theate us sying and
also at theate using with name like some
name given and in the use case 3 I all
mandatory have to use us sying with
name I don't want my developers to get
confused right what uh what to
follow so there is very another simple
way and this is I would say that mostly
industry standard
so what it was says
that I always want to set my executor as
default
one right no matter whether if you use
usync or at theate usync
name doesn't matter only my executor
will get picked up okay so there is
another way so another way is that
during the configuration class app
config Implement a sync
configurer implement this
class okay and once you implement this
class you have to override this method
get a sync
executor now since you have overread
this m get a sync
executor this is now your threadpool
executor you can put whether thread pool
task executor or you can use threadpool
uh plain Java threadpool executor you
can use anything uh right return type
should be executor either you can use
plain Java threadpool executor or
threadpool task executor whatever the
now you want it you can use
it now what happened with this is that
even if you using atate ay sync right
always this will get picked up so you
never have to worry about hey I am using
plain Java here now since I am using
plain Java I have to specifically
mention the name what is the my
threadpool executor name now that worry
goes now you don't have to worry about
whether plain Java or threadpool task
executor spring
one now since you have done that uh
override this one now your method get
invoked to decide which executor to use
since we have overrided this now the
control will come here and this executor
will
use and that would be our default one it
will always find an
Executor okay and also remember one
thing here if you are using this
approach very very important since this
is not a bean and here we are creating a
new object every time since this see
this is just an override method this is
not a bean you know that bean by default
is single
turn and here we have to take care of
that so I have created a private
threadpool executor object if threadpool
executor is null then only I am creating
an object if object is already present
then return it and I have created this
method as synchronized so that if two
threads are coming two requests are
coming
parall they will get only one object for
my threadpool executor so only this hand
hand Ling required if you are using this
okay so this is another industry
standard so in if you are working in
your company you might see this also
in uh like developers are using this
right so this is also an acceptable way
of working Implement aing configure but
take care of the singl turnon here you
have to take it manually and but in the
above one at since we are using at
theate bean bean are by default single
turn so that is automatically taken
care
so that is one way where you can avoid
like I don't have to give name what is
the use case one use case two use case
three you will always use at the rateing
and it will always pick your
executor okay so this is just an output
I showed I am using here Java Java
threadpool executor and even though I'm
using at theate using mine got picked up
not simple using task
executor okay do practice it with your
hand and in the part two I will cover
that there are some more topics I want
to cover in this exception handling
using method return type transaction
management with the using
method and there are some interview
questions so that I will cover in the
part two part but I hope this is totally
clear like answer is not always a
straightforward like spring boot uses
default simple assing task execution no
there is more to it okay guys any
question please feel free to ping me in
the comment section we can discuss more
thank you bye